<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Blog of Bernardas Ališauskas</title><link href="https://granitas.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://granitas.github.io/feeds/bernardas-alisauskas.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://granitas.github.io/</id><updated>2016-10-10T00:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Going to Pycon Poland!</title><link href="https://granitas.github.io/pycon-pl.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-10T00:00:00+02:00</published><author><name>Bernardas Ališauskas</name></author><id>tag:granitas.github.io,2016-10-10:pycon-pl.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last year in Euro-Python 2015 someone from PyconPL had a lightning talk about PyconPL and since that moment I was sold. However I missed it by few days. This year however, I'm going and I'm taking a short vacation to explore Warsaw too!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a bunch of info about the conference on the &lt;a href="https://pl.pycon.org/2016/about_en.html"&gt;official page&lt;/a&gt; and I don't want to be redundant, but the venue looks awesome and in overall the event looks pretty huge. Primarily I just wanted to share how much money do you need to attend something like this, how do you get there and lastly whether it is worth it.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The route&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Trip route from Tartu to Warsaw" src="https://granitas.github.io/images/pycon-pl-travel.png" /&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we're taking a bus from Tartu -&amp;gt; Riga which is really the most tedious part of this trip. As you can see in the image the trip almost takes &lt;strong&gt;4 hours&lt;/strong&gt; and the bus leaves early and often is packed full. We'll spend two hours in Riga's airport waiting for our flight, which I really don't mind since Riga's airport is really nice. And to finish it off we'll take a &lt;strong&gt;1.25&lt;/strong&gt; hour long flight to Warsaw itself. I love flying, more accurately I like take offs and landings so having such short flights, where majority of the time will be the take off and the landing, sounds great!&lt;br /&gt;
In conclusion, we leave at 7:00 and we should be in Warsaw at 14:35 (warsaw's time). So this ends up being &lt;strong&gt;8.5 hours for 900km&lt;/strong&gt; which really doesn't have a good hour/km ratio per se but considering the down-times and the location it really isn't bad at all! &lt;br /&gt;
Lastly the conference organizes a bus that will take us from Warsaw to Ossa village, which is few kilometers away from Warsaw and there the conference itself will be held. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Cost&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conference&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I was a bit late to register and missed the early bird prices, I had to drop 211€ per person (422€ for two people) for 4 days of the conference, including food and accommodation. This might seem like a lot but compared to other conferences is really little. &lt;br /&gt;
I actually chatted with one of the hosts a bit and he mentioned that pretty much the whole fee goes to the hotel that is hosting the conference, after visiting the website I can understand that since it advertises the rooms at 90€ a night the conference fee seems to be very reasonable indeed!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Travel&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plane tickets from Riga to Warsaw and back ended up being 62€ per person(125€ for two) which is slightly above from the best I could find. At one point I got 42€ deals pop up but the payment didn't go through and the next day it popped to 62€. I know airline websites are really fishy when it comes to pricing, storing profiles and cookies to jack up the price whenever they see fit but I'm certain this was just an unfortunate coincidence.&lt;br /&gt;
The bus to Riga from Tartu ended up being 30€ per person (60€ in total) both ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So &lt;strong&gt;total ended up being 303€ per person&lt;/strong&gt; which is pretty cheap for a conference 906km away!&lt;br /&gt;
This doesn't include any traveling expenses which I'll be sure to calculated and include in aftermath blogpost!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last python conference I went to was EuroPython 2015 and it was super fun, mostly because I got to meet a bunch of coworkers from Scrapinghub, I hope PyconPL can live up to the hype and I'll be sure to post about it either way.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="pycon"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="poland"></category><category term="travel"></category></entry><entry><title>First post. Hello Pelican!</title><link href="https://granitas.github.io/installing-pelican.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-09T00:00:00+02:00</published><author><name>Bernardas Ališauskas</name></author><id>tag:granitas.github.io,2016-10-09:installing-pelican.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've decided to start a blog after Python package called Pelican caught my eye.&lt;br /&gt;
Pelican is a tool to generate a static blog from reStructuredText or Markdown input files. And most importantly it looks to be really fun, full python with jinja2 templating, which means it's fully extendable, configurable and modifiable as it's under GPL license.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Installing Pelican&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pelicans are cool" src="https://granitas.github.io/images/pelican-bird.jpg" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The setup for &lt;code&gt;Pelican&lt;/code&gt; is pretty straightforward just run:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;~&amp;gt; pip install pelican  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Installing Pelican package for python&lt;/span&gt;
~&amp;gt; mdir blog &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; blog  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Create and jump into your blog directory!&lt;/span&gt;
~/blog/&amp;gt; pelican-quickstart
    ... &lt;span class="c1"&gt;#answer some simple questions here&lt;/span&gt;
~/blog/&amp;gt; vim content/first-page.md
    ... &lt;span class="c1"&gt;#write your blog here in simple markdown&lt;/span&gt;
~/blog/&amp;gt; pelican content  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# regenerate website&lt;/span&gt;
~/blog/&amp;gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; output
~/blog/output&amp;gt; python -m pelican.server  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# run pelican server to test locally&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now connect to &lt;code&gt;http://localhost:8000&lt;/code&gt; and there you go!&lt;br /&gt;
You can check &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/en/latest/content.html#articles-and-pages"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for how to template your message how to format your blog entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Vim markdown highlight for .md files&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While going through the installation I've noticed that markdown doesn't have highlighting in vim which was peculiar. I found &lt;a href="http://superuser.com/questions/701496/no-syntax-highlight-on-md-files"&gt;this post which describes a simple fix&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
Simply create directories and file: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;~/.vim/ftdetect/markdown.vim
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;with content: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;au BufNewFile,BufRead *.md  setf markdown
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Theming Pelican&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The default Pelican theme is pretty great however I stumbled on &lt;a href="https://github.com/alexandrevicenzi/Flex"&gt;flex-theme&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href="https://github.com/getpelican/pelican-themes"&gt;pelican theme repo&lt;/a&gt; on github. So that's my choice for now, but I'd like to touch up the color scheme a bit. Check out &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/en/stable/pelican-themes.html"&gt;&lt;code&gt;pelican-themes&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Configuring Pelican&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of bells and whistles come straight out of the box with the pelican and your theme. For example to setup Disqus commnets all I had to do is add &lt;code&gt;DISQUS_SITENAME = "granitosaurus"&lt;/code&gt; where &lt;code&gt;granitosaurus&lt;/code&gt; is my registered name of my disqus account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Publishing Pelican&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Pelican generates a static webpage you can use anything to publish it. I decided to use &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/en/stable/tips.html#user-pages"&gt;github user pages&lt;/a&gt; which is a bit more complicated than the docs make it out to be. For user pages I like to keep the whole source code in branch &lt;code&gt;source&lt;/code&gt; and keep the generated output in &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; as per github's user pages rule. Then use &lt;code&gt;ghp-import&lt;/code&gt; to automatically update master code with the most recent  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;git&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;checkout&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;source&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;pelican&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;o&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;output&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;c&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;publishconf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;py&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ghp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;output&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;master&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The above will make source branch, generate blog and push the output to &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; so it's viewable at https://username.github.io &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE&lt;/strong&gt; The most important bit is to set &lt;code&gt;SITEURL&lt;/code&gt; in your &lt;code&gt;publishconf.py&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;https://username.github.io&lt;/code&gt; make sure it's &lt;strong&gt;HTTPS&lt;/strong&gt; since default SITEURL generated by pelican is http and github pages requires https. This took me an hour of messing around to finally figure out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Wrap Up&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far Pelican took quite a bit of work to get things going. It looks quite simple but there's a bunch of little quirks that are really hard to debug. It's not as easy as starting up a wordpress blog but it's quite fun and it seems to be really flexible. &lt;br /&gt;
Let's see if it pays off! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Checkout the source for more at https://github.com/Granitas/granitas.github.io/tree/source&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="pelican"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="blog"></category></entry></feed>