<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Blog of Bernardas Ališauskas - self</title><link href="https://granitosaurus.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="Blog%20of%20Bernardas%20Ali%C5%A1auskas/feeds/self.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://granitosaurus.github.io/</id><updated>2019-10-26T00:00:00+02:00</updated><subtitle>Python programmer and a goof who loves free software, video-games and heavy metal</subtitle><entry><title>Get Organized With TaskWarrior!</title><link href="https://granitosaurus.github.io/taskwarrior-intro.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-10-26T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-10-26T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Bernardas Ališauskas</name></author><id>tag:granitosaurus.github.io,2019-10-26:/taskwarrior-intro.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Quick introduction how to get productive and organized with amazing commandline tool called Taskwarrior!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you've been part of terminal ecosystem for you're most likely familiar with numerous terminal &lt;em&gt;todo&lt;/em&gt; sort of programs. I'd like to introduce you to king of all of them &lt;a href="https://taskwarrior.org/"&gt;Taskwarrior&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;br/&gt;
The name might sound intimidating but don't go - it's quite the opposite: it's butter smooth!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="intro"&gt;Intro&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your key command here is &lt;code&gt;task&lt;/code&gt;. Typing this alone will list your open tasks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ task

ID Age  Description                    Urg 
&lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; 32s   write a blog about taskwarrior    &lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="m"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; 11s   make carrot cake                  &lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="m"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; 2s    pay electric bills                &lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the rest of cli goes as intuitive as it follows, these are your 3 vital beginner commands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;add "some task"&lt;/code&gt; - to add a task.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;done &amp;lt;id&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; - to close task.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;modify &amp;lt;id&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; - change something about task.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally Taskwarrior has one vital important feature for managing your tasks - &lt;strong&gt;tags&lt;/strong&gt;. You simply specify tags with &lt;code&gt;+&lt;/code&gt; signs in front of your commands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ task +work add &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"fix linkedin.com crawler"&lt;/span&gt;
$ task +work 
ID Age  Description                    Urg 
&lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;  2s   fix linkedin.com crawler        &lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see already with these 4 little things: add, list, modify, tags - you have great powers. Time for example workflow!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="example workflow"&gt;Example Workflow&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a simple version of my taskwarrior workflow; First add tasks the moment you get them and try to split them up into small tasks - you're not an idiot you won't get confused don't worry:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ task add +work &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"fix project1"&lt;/span&gt;
Created task &lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;.

$ task add +work &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"msg admin about project1 dump"&lt;/span&gt;
Created task &lt;span class="m"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;.

$ task add +shop &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"potatoes - for potato cannon"&lt;/span&gt;
Created task &lt;span class="m"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;.

$ task add +me &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"1 chapter of new book"&lt;/span&gt;
Created task &lt;span class="m"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;.

$ task add +me &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"wash dishes"&lt;/span&gt;
Created task &lt;span class="m"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;.

$ task add +gf &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"research christmas present on etsy"&lt;/span&gt;
Created task &lt;span class="m"&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;.

$ task add +me &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"practice bass a bit"&lt;/span&gt;
Created task &lt;span class="m"&gt;7&lt;/span&gt;.

$ task
ID Age  Tag  Description                        Urg 
&lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; 7min work fix project1                        &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;.8
&lt;span class="m"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; 6min work msg admin about project1 dump       &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;.8
&lt;span class="m"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; 6min shop potatoes - &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; potato cannon        &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;.8
&lt;span class="m"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt; 5min me   &lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; chapter of new book               &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;.8
&lt;span class="m"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt; 5min me   wash dishes                         &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;.8
&lt;span class="m"&gt;6&lt;/span&gt; 4min gf   research christmas present on etsy  &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;.8
&lt;span class="m"&gt;7&lt;/span&gt; 4min me   practice bass a bit                 &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;.8 
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right, got bunch of tasks and now just pop them as you feel like. Having a weekday work day? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ task +work
ID Age   Tag  Description                   Urg 
&lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; 11min work fix project1                   &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;.8
&lt;span class="m"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; 10min work msg admin about project1 dump  &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;.8
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Task 1 really needs to get done: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ task start &lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
Starting task &lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'fix project1'&lt;/span&gt;.
Started &lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; task.
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All this does is mark the task in your list that it's "ongoing"&lt;/em&gt; :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ task +work
ID Active Age   Tag  Description                   Urg 
 &lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; 1min   14min work fix project1                   &lt;span class="m"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;.8
 &lt;span class="m"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;        13min work msg admin about project1 dump  &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;.8
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Been working hard for an hour or so, time for a short break. Lets keep the task active so we could jump right back in after our break and take a look at &lt;code&gt;me&lt;/code&gt; tasks we have for our break:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ task +me 
ID Age   Tag Description           Urg 
 &lt;span class="m"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt; 14min me  &lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; chapter of new book  &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;.8    
 &lt;span class="m"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt; 14min me  wash dishes            &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;.8
 &lt;span class="m"&gt;7&lt;/span&gt; 12min me  practice bass a bit    &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;.8
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great time to boot up the bass for a song or two and while &lt;em&gt;Rocksmith on ps4&lt;/em&gt; is booting up - wash the dishes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ task &lt;span class="m"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;done&lt;/span&gt;
Completed task &lt;span class="m"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'wash dishes'&lt;/span&gt;.
Completed &lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; task.
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Break over, simply jump back to work, the task you've been working on is still glowing red there waiting for you ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="get micro motivated!"&gt;Get Micro Motivated!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taskwarrior allows this sort of dead-simple micro-motivation. It's so simple an intuitive that in never feels like &lt;em&gt;additional&lt;/em&gt; work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often it's easy to go through your day without having tangible experience of your accomplishments. No matter how small your tasks are - the day feels so much better when you can visualize and feel the tiny hills you've conquered!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="further reading"&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taskwarrior also packs a bunch of awesome, rich features but those are beyond the scope of this blog post.&lt;br/&gt;
Taskwarrior documentation is well written and quite short:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;intro: https://taskwarrior.org/docs/introduction.html&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;30 second tutorial: https://taskwarrior.org/docs/30second.html&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;example workflows of users: https://taskwarrior.org/docs/workflow.html&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;man task&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bugwarrior plugin for pulling issues from other sources - https://bugwarrior.readthedocs.io/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="productivity"></category><category term="linux"></category></entry><entry><title>1 Year in Chiang Mai, Thailand</title><link href="https://granitosaurus.github.io/chiang-mai-1.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-02T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-06-02T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Bernardas Ališauskas</name></author><id>tag:granitosaurus.github.io,2019-06-02:/chiang-mai-1.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My experience of living 1 year in Chiang Mai, Thailand for 1 year now.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been living in Chiang Mai - biggest city in North Thailand - for over one year now. I did a lot during this year and experienced many things. The food is great, the housing is cool and the language is complicated. Let me tell you all about it! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="visa and getting here"&gt;Visa And Getting Here&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting to Chiang Mai is dead easy - take a flight to Bangkok and then another one straight to Chiang Mai! There are flights almost every hour and are surprisingly cheap. The flight from Europe (e.g. Riga) - Bangkok is around 350&amp;euro; + Bangkok - Chiang Mai 50&amp;euro; = &lt;strong&gt;~400&amp;euro;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Visa it's a bit more complicated. There are several types of visa but the most interesting ones:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tourist visa"&gt;Tourist Visa&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone can get this visa. You can either get 30 days on arrival visa or submit your passport with ~50&amp;euro; and get a 60 days visa with a possibility of 30 days extension for another ~50&amp;euro;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's one thing to note though. For tourist visa you need:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Onwards Ticket - some transportation ticket out of the country&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Financial Proof - that you have some money (bank statement or cash)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hotel Reservation/Address - this one is rather weird as you can just enter random hotel address.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/tourist-to-officer.png"&gt;&lt;img src="/images/tourist-to-officer.png" title="You really don't want to mess with a guy that spends 8 hours a day in a chair stamping documents!"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;You really don't want to mess with a guy that spends 8 hours a day in a chair stamping documents!&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've started with this visa one year ago by taking my passport to Thai embassy in Hanoi and getting it back with a visa next day -&amp;gt; easy peasy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="education visa"&gt;Education Visa&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is visa you can get by applying to study something. This can be almost anything but usually it's either Thai language or self-defense training like Thai boxing (Muai-Thai).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is actually very cool idea as it setup this little education infrastructure for foreigners. You can stay here as long as you study something of ours! Pretty awesome!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are either proper schools or "visa farms" that really don't do any real teaching and only provide you documents to get your visa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The great bit about student visas that they are kinda "eternal" (some suggest that after 3-4 years you might start to be dnied) - as long as you are studying you can extend your visa for 90 days for ~50&amp;euro;. It only takes few hours of your day to get it done and you're set!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="getting my education visa"&gt;Getting My Education Visa&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've picked up the best rated school in Chiang Mai called &lt;a href="http://manathaischool.co.th"&gt;Mana Thai School&lt;/a&gt;, dropped &lt;strong&gt;~750&amp;euro; for a yearly course&lt;/strong&gt; which involved 2 hour lessons 4-times a week and found out a rather bizarre initial process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With school contract in hand and tourist visa in my passport I found out that to acquire student visa I need to leave Thailand and apply for it in Thai embassy - here started my unexpected travel to Laos!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/chiang-mai_to_vientiane.png"&gt;&lt;img src="/images/chiang-mai_to_vientiane.png" title="flight-&amp;gt;bus-&amp;gt;tuk tuk-&amp;gt;bus-&amp;gt;taxi-&amp;gt;flight"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;flight-&amp;gt;bus-&amp;gt;tuk tuk-&amp;gt;bus-&amp;gt;taxi-&amp;gt;flight&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is called visa run - you leave the country to apply for a new tourist/education visa. The most common one is going to Thai embassy in capital of Laos - Vientianne and it's awkward, stressful and surprisingly expensive journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took me two flights, couple of bus rides and one expensive taxi ride to not miss my flight back. I also got ripped off at the border by being required to buy visa because the workers didn't know what Lithuania was. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/vientiane-morning.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="/images/vientiane-morning.jpg" title="waiting for the wrong embassy to open"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;waiting for the wrong embassy to open&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally I went to the wrong embassy early in the morning, so when I finally got to the real one I spent 8 or so hours in a queue to get my passport and request to study submitted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/vientiane-day.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="/images/vientiane-day.jpg" title="there is some interesting sight-seeing to do!"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;there is some interesting sight-seeing to do!&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the rest of the day I explored Vientiane which was quite tiny but cosy. It's was a pleasant mix of Thailand and Vietnam but not as exciting, busy or captivating like either. After exploring Pagodas, historic buildings, parks and markets I had enough but I'd definitely would come back to spend there a week or so.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="studying thai_1"&gt;Studying Thai&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've spent almost a whole year learning Thai and it was quite fun. Thai is a very unusual language for my background - it's my first tonal language and it's quite a barrier!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been studying 2 hours a day for 4 days a week in a group of 5-10 people at &lt;a href="http://manathaischool.co.th"&gt;Manna Thai School&lt;/a&gt;. The first two months we learned just plain talking and some writing in latin'ish alphabet - it was great fun. After writing and reading started and things got much more complicated quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/thai-alphabet.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="/images/thai-alphabet.jpg" title="every letter has an official word attached to it. Like Z for Zebra but standartized which is really great for learning!"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;every letter has an official word attached to it. Like Z for Zebra but standartized which is really great for learning!&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thai writing system is very unique and fun but also very dated and filled with old rules, exceptions and dead letters. Some interesting facts about Thai language:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thai language is a &lt;strong&gt;tonal language&lt;/strong&gt; and has 4 different tones, which means your tone can be the difference between a horse or a dog or between number two and a brothel. Tones are really hard to as rules are complicated and even most native thai speakers don't know them and just talk by ear.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are &lt;strong&gt;46 consonant letters&lt;/strong&gt; in Thai but only 21 consonant sounds, which means you have multiple letters for same consonant and they are not interchangeable, i.e. you have to use correct letter T (there are 6 T letters) from in word Turtle or you might end up writing something else entirely.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are &lt;strong&gt;dead letters&lt;/strong&gt; that are either completely dead or used in very few words.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thai &lt;strong&gt;vowels can go in any direction&lt;/strong&gt;: left, right, up, bottom! Unlike most languages that simple go from left to right in order thai is very peculiar and instead you write consonant and attach 1 of many different vowels that have fixed location around the consonant (e.g. long U goes under a consonant while short a goes above it)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are &lt;strong&gt;no spaces between words&lt;/strong&gt; in written thai which makes reading as a beginner really difficult.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/thai-love-you.png"&gt;&lt;img "pom="" (from="" i="" in="" kun"="" like="" love="" male's="" perspective)"="" rak="" something="" sounds="" src="/images/thai-love-you.png" thai,="" title="Words " writen="" you"=""/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Words "I love you" writen in Thai, sounds something like "pom rak kun" (from male's perspective)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All that being said it's a fun language and I enjoy learning it, it's just not a very good one and definitely in need of some reforms. Neighbouring countries of Laos and Myanmar use similar languages with few reforms and they are known to be much more sane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/mana-400h.png"&gt;&lt;img src="/images/mana-400h.png" title="It's a great deal; 400 hours definitely seems a lot!"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;It's a great deal; 400 hours definitely seems a lot!&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On paper I did 400 hours of classes but I'll be honest - I've been skipping a few classes. That being said I got quite a bit done. I'm quite satisfied with my current elementary-school level writing/reading and some basic talking/listening. I think I can pick it up to a rather fluent level in another year. according to &lt;a href="https://blog.thelinguist.com/how-long-should-it-take-to-learn-a-language"&gt;FSI source&lt;/a&gt; to acquire &lt;strong&gt;basic fluency&lt;/strong&gt; in Thai you need around &lt;strong&gt;720 hours&lt;/strong&gt;. So I'm trying not to beat myself up too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Main problem is actually practicing Thai. It's surprisingly difficult to immerse yourself in the language if you don't actively put effort into it. I've been working on extending this with some training apps and tv shows on Netflix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall Thai language is fun and I'm glad I picked it up. It's unusual writing system, tonal pronunciation and word order is a great mind exercise!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I'm in the works of writing a blog about all thai language learning tools I've tried, there are few good ones!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="lodging"&gt;Lodging&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this year I lived in three different condos and all of them were great value! The quality condo pricing ranges from &lt;strong&gt;270 - 550&amp;euro;&lt;/strong&gt;. If you want nice location, pool, gym, rec space(like library or park) and a bit more space then 500&amp;euro; with a yearly contract is a fair number - and that's an absolute steal!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All three condos I lived in all had pools, great staff, security and great location! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="todo"&gt;Prompt Condo&lt;/a&gt; - had great location was cosy but not very luxurious - 420&amp;euro;/month. It has a cosy pool on ground floor and a little gym right above it. No shared space like library or a garden though.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/prompt-condo.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="/images/prompt-condo.jpg" title="pool and a gym on second floor. It's quite cosy"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;pool and a gym on second floor. It's quite cosy&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="todo"&gt;Play Condo&lt;/a&gt; - my favorite experience in Chiang Mai. It's not very big but the staff was always helpful, the room for 560&amp;euro; was pretty huge (50m&amp;sup2; or so) and the rooftop pool and library is a real pleasure. The location was close to perfect too - across the street of night market and a super mall.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/play-condo.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="/images/play-condo.jpg" title="rainy day near the pool is perfect for relaxing!"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;rainy day near the pool is perfect for relaxing!&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="todo"&gt;Escent Condo&lt;/a&gt; - I had to move to a different town area and found this new condo that is 26 stories high and is pretty much empty. For 460&amp;euro; you get around 40m&amp;sup2; of living space with nice view plus a rooftop pool/sauna, libary and gym. It's right next to huge super mall and few local markets too. The only down-side is that it's a bit far from a city center.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/escent-condo.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="/images/escent-condo.jpg" title="26th floor really delivers a nice sunset!"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;26th floor really delivers a nice sunset!&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found the condominium infrastructure very impressive and enjoyable. I'd have trouble going back to european style flats and for this price it's worth staying here just for the housing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/cosy-condo.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="/images/cosy-condo.jpg" title="a perfect spot for an afternoon nap!"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;a perfect spot for an afternoon nap!&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The general cost is very affordable. You can find similar condos in 300&amp;euro; range too if you're more flexible with location. It's worth noting that electricity bills can add up really fast so you should add 30&amp;euro; or so for air-conditioning alone!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="food"&gt;Food&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This segment probably deserves a blog post of it's own but to put it shortly thai food is great and surprisingly supportive of vegetarian diet, though egg is very prevalent so vegan diet is a bit harder.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thai food is very rich in taste, be it salty, sweet or sour. It's relative healthy too - maybe a bit heavy on saturated fats (oil) and carbs (rice) but if you can pay a bit attention you can have a very healthy vegetarian diet without much effort!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/cheap_food.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="/images/cheap_food.jpg" title="7&amp;euro; for two days worth of delicious, vegetarian food!"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;7&amp;euro; for two days worth of delicious, vegetarian food!&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest appeal is sheer value. I often take a backpack full of plastic containers and fill them up with various dishes at a local vegetarian restaurant. For &lt;strong&gt;8&amp;euro;&lt;/strong&gt; and can eat quality, delicious and somewhat healthy food &lt;strong&gt;for 2-3 days&lt;/strong&gt;! The best part is that it saves a bunch of time too!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly &lt;strong&gt;being vegetarian in Thailand isn't hard at all&lt;/strong&gt; but some effort is required. Thai people really like to eat meat so they tend to mix some meat into every dish which is hard to avoid unless you can communicate with staff to adjust the dish for you which they don't mind doing. The word for vegetarian is &lt;strong&gt;เจ&lt;/strong&gt; (pronounced &lt;em&gt;jėė&lt;/em&gt;) which stand for buddhist vegetarian diet.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/thai-jee.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="/images/thai-jee.jpg" title="signs used to indicated vegatrian (jee) restaurant"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;signs used to indicated vegatrian (jee) restaurant&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to find some delicious, cheap vegetarian food is looking for this word (usually in yellow background) around Temples - the restaurants/cafeterias serve the best vegetarian thai food there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="produce"&gt;Produce&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vegetables and fruits in Chiang Mai are highly seasonal, though mostly by price and quality not by availability. There are two seasons in Thailand - wet and dry but for plants it's a bit more complicated. There are these, as I'd describe, "surge" months where specific vegetable or fruit is really kicking off and you can just drown yourself in it. As of writing of this blog the Lichee season is starting and thai lichee are absolutely delicious!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/thai-market.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="/images/thai-market.jpg" title="Produce stalls are everywhere! [1]"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Produce stalls are everywhere! [1]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The local markets (which are everywhere) offer a lot of quality produce for pennies - especially if you go out a bit out of town or go to wholesale markets. Some produce is a bit harder to get by at times but can be found at bigger markets or at some import shop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite produce related experience is that often local alleys have small stalls of good quality produce, so if you're in a sudden need you can just pop down from your condo and grab some carrots or whatever you're missing for that delicious soup your cooking!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For other favorite experiences here's few of my favorite produce from top of my head: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mango - green mango is pleasantly sour and great snack dipped in sauce or spice mixes, while yellow mango is perfect sweetness on it's own.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Baby mango - it's just young green mango but you can eat them like apples, they are quite sour and very refreshing. Usually people eat them with sweet tamarind sauce.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lychee/Longan - there are many kinds, some sweeter some less so but all of them are delicious and super cheap when in season!    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Guava - apple of thailand. Packs more vitamin c than a lemon!  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pineapple - Chiang Rai (a town north of CM) is probably the world capital of pineapples. There are so many kinds and many different tastes! The baby ones are especially delicious as they lack of protein that burns your mouth.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mangosteen - these little guys just melt your mouth! They are quite seasonal and difficult to peel but are absolutely worth it!  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Salads - if you're into salads CM got you covered, I'm eating Red Coral almost daily! There are also many salad bars and make your own salad restaurants like &lt;a href="https://www.google.com/maps/search/okaju+chiang+mai"&gt;Okaju&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.google.com/maps/search/salad+concept+chiang+mai"&gt;Salad Concept&lt;/a&gt; where you can get bowl of delicious, dressed salad for 2&amp;euro;!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eggplants - there are lot of different eggplants and they're all delicious. If you know your way around a kitchen you can really go wild with these guys!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Berries - there aren't many berries in Thailand but few that do exist are extremely delicious. Mulberries and Cape Gooseberries are to die for! Unfortunately just like everywhere berries here are highly seasonal too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mushrooms - there are many different mushrooms in varying tastes but all of them are delicious! My favorites are just sauted or fried with butter and chilly powder. Eringi mushroom is my daily protein driver!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another absolutely delicious use of produce is &lt;strong&gt;pickling&lt;/strong&gt;. You can find almost pickled anything - mango, tamarind, grapes and all sorts of plume-like tiny little fruits I don't even know the name of!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/thai-pickled.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="/images/thai-pickled.jpg" title="Add some chilly powder and sugal mix and you got yourself a perfect snack!"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Add some chilly powder and sugal mix and you got yourself a perfect snack!&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All that beings said some produce is surprisingly disappointing. Tomato is my favourite fruit and thai tomatoes aren't great, they are never proper ripe and aren't as watery as imported ones. Another disappointing thing is serious lack of canned legumes, beans etc. - it's awfully expensive and not as great as you would get back in europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="weeds/leafs/flowers"&gt;Weeds/leafs/flowers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are so many little obscure plants that Thai like to deep or stir fry or mix in some curry. I could hardly do it justice in this small section but variety is truly astonishing. &lt;br/&gt;
If you take a thai cook to a local jungle and ask them to start pointing at edible plants you'd be surprised to see them turn into a helicopter. &lt;br/&gt;
Stir fry pan is probably the ultimate survival tool for thai outdoors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most basic but absolutely delicious dish is simple omelet, mixed in with some of these obscurities eaten with some chilly sauce and rice. It's has been an easy breakfast/lunch for when you want some &lt;em&gt;heavy&lt;/em&gt; food - pop in to veggie stall at your alley to get some plants and sticky rice, toss the plants in an omelet and combined that with some sauce and sticky rice you have a carb and fat rich, delicious, and most importantly - lazy, lunch!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another one of my favorite dishes called Nam Niau is a soup made with dried flower called Niau, literal dish translation &lt;em&gt;water Niau&lt;/em&gt; and it's delicious! usually combined with rice noodles, tomatoes and some extras like liver or in vegetarian versions mushrooms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/thai-nam-niau.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="/images/thai-nam-niau.jpg" title="Niau flower soup is different everywhere I tried but the core soup is always as delicious as you expect it! [1]"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Niau flower soup is different everywhere I tried but the core soup is always as delicious as you expect it! [1]&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="coffee and tea"&gt;Coffee and Tea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thailand is full of Tea and Coffee plantations and they grow some of the most delicious stuff in the world! Not only that but these plantations tend to be a fun place to visit and often have a little place to get some dinner with a view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/cm_tea-plantation.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="/images/cm_tea-plantation.jpg" title="an hour drive to the mountains for breathtaking lunch over a tea plantation"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;an hour drive to the mountains for breathtaking lunch over a tea plantation&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thailand really shines in this regard, some of the best Arabica coffee in the world can be found here in North Thailand. The mountains are just tall and accommodating enough to produce great quality beans that are further roasted and taken care of families and hill tribes that have been doing this for generations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coffee is really cheap too if avoid the tourist brands. A 500g pack high quality arabica from a hill tribe (you can even find some in nearby super market) will only cost you 3&amp;euro;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The caf&amp;egrave; scene in Chiang Mai is very healthy too. There are a lot of little coffee shops sprinkled around even at the most remote corners of the country. All serving good, delicious coffee 1-3&amp;euro; and often provide an either themed or cosy to sit down to drink it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/cm_geese-friends.jpg"&gt;&lt;img and="" art="" birds="" company"="" geese="" has="" keeping="" other="" roastery"="" src="/images/cm_geese-friends.jpg" title="my favorite caf&amp;eacute; " you=""/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;my favorite caf&amp;eacute; "Art Roastery" has geese and other birds keeping you company&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I work remotely I often do that from a caf&amp;eacute;. The best cafes in my experience are located towards Doi Suthep mountain, so if you enjoy caf&amp;eacute; hoping that's the direction you should aim at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="the smog_1"&gt;The Smog&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far most of the things I said about Chiang Mai were very much positive. It's absolutely true - Chiang Mai is wonderful for the bigger part of the year but starting around January &lt;strong&gt;burning season&lt;/strong&gt; starts and goes on until late May. It's terrible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/cm_dirty-clean.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="/images/cm_dirty-clean.jpg" title="March compared to end of May"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;March compared to end of May&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's ugly, but not only that it's just awfully unhealthy and the smog has a very unpleasant smell which makes any outdoors activity really unpleasant. Burning season is also &lt;em&gt;high&lt;/em&gt; season with more tourists coming from cold countries to enjoy Thai sunshine - means prices are often higher and the town is packed more than usual.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Combined these two things I couldn't recommend anyone coming to Chiang Mai during the burning season, in fact I'd recommend leaving it for South Thailand or neighbouring countries.&lt;br/&gt;
That being said some few people are absolute fine with it so personal tolerance definitely plays a role here.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="leisure time and conclusions"&gt;Leisure Time and Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of things to do in Chiang Mai, most of it involves the beautiful nature of North Thailand but there's good amount of entertainment too. Chiang Mai has many shopping malls that provides relatively cheap and enjoyable shopping experience, there are some activities and events happening every week. There's a healthy music scene and a sizable expat community for various activities ranging from board-game evenings to book and yoga clubs.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/cm-lake.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="/images/cm-lake.jpg" title="cosy little lake almost at the city center"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;cosy little lake almost at the city center&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarise Chiang Mai is a really fun, affordable and cosy town. The housing is amazing so is the food and nature. It's a great place to live in for 8/12 months and you really have to hermit your way through the 4 months of burning season (or ideally leave) but this can be planned around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The year I spent here was really enjoyable with the exception of burning season. I really enjoy North Thailand nature and there's always some new place to explore. I got driver license, scooter and a car which I believe are vital to truly enjoy the exploration and nature aspect of the area (maybe you could do without a car but with big bike instead).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I plan to stay here longer so there are many more blogpost to come! I plan to cover some subjects like expenses, food and my favorite activities in greater detail. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more Chiang My photos check out my &lt;a href="https://pixelfed.social/Wraptile"&gt;pixelfed feed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="credits and attributions"&gt;Credits and attributions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 - https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Takeaway&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="travel"></category><category term="thailand"></category><category term="chiang-mai"></category></entry><entry><title>Quest Accepted: Travel to HCMC, Vietnam</title><link href="https://granitosaurus.github.io/quest-hcmc.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-01-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Bernardas Ališauskas</name></author><id>tag:granitosaurus.github.io,2018-01-18:/quest-hcmc.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My and my girlfriend's struggle to get to Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Me and my girlfriend are spending 3 months in Vietnam this year (amount tourist visa allows you) and our first stop is the biggest city in Vietnam, and the biggest city we've been to in general!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="quest #1: getting there"&gt;Quest #1: Getting There&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our original plan was to go fly out from Tartu to Helsinki, chill there for 8 hours (literally) then take an 8 hour flight to Bangkok, chill there for two hours (literally too, air conditioning is strong in asia) and finally take a two hour flight to HCMC.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/MeJzHSxRq40" width="560"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It didn't go exactly as planned.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we left to Helsinki we did a final checkup and turns out our flight carrier Jetstar does not offer online check-in for our trip - this means we would have to leave the international area of the airport, check in, get back to the international area, and get to our gate for the flight. 
To leave the international area you need to get a visa and we only had 2 hours there so there would have been almost no way for us to make it... Well so we thought. Even Jetstar support "specialist" assured us that is the case:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"you need to get out to check in, would you like to reschedule for an extra fee?". &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless we found it a bit hard to believe and went to reddit, asked some people who had done these kinds of trips before on &lt;a href="http://reddit.com/r/digitalnomads"&gt;/r/digitalnomads&lt;/a&gt; and turns out big airports like the one in Bangkok have check-in booths &lt;strong&gt;in&lt;/strong&gt; the international areas so we didn't have worry about anything! Crisis Averted!   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;video autoplay="" height="240" loop="" muted="" title="Close call though!" width="480"&gt;&lt;source src="https://granitosaurus.github.io/gifs/spongebob_crisis.mp4" type="video/mp4"/&gt;&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well we weren't too certain, but we were at least somewhat relieved. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However our adventure was not over.&lt;br/&gt;
Once we got to &lt;strong&gt;Helsinki&lt;/strong&gt; we found out that everything &lt;strong&gt;is really bloody expensive&lt;/strong&gt;! We chilled in a mall near the airport for 8 hours trying to not go bankrupt and it was a &lt;em&gt;long&lt;/em&gt;, dull experience. Also I got a bit of a fever so that definitely didn't make it any more exciting.&lt;br/&gt;
Finally we decided to go to the airport early, which was a great idea as the &lt;strong&gt;buses in Finland don't stop unless you put your hand out&lt;/strong&gt; and wave at them like your life depends on it. &lt;br/&gt;
Needless to say we missed our bus because we were not aware of this great ritual of Finnish people and enjoyed 25 more minutes of lovely Finnish weather.&lt;br/&gt;
Waving hands at busses? Pretty barbaric if you ask me.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;video autoplay="" loop="" muted="" title="I guess this episode was written by someone who has been in Finaland" width="480"&gt;&lt;source src="https://granitosaurus.github.io/gifs/spongebob_bus.mp4" type="video/mp4"/&gt;&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's more!&lt;br/&gt;
Finally we got onto our plane from Helsinki to Bangkok. It was a nice plane and the flight went pretty smooth, except that we were late. The flight wasn't delayed or anything but we were almost an hour late for whatever reason.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We landed on time to still make it, still had an hour before check in closes, "We did it" so we've thought. Well our plane couldn't park for another 30 minutes as a plane in front of us had to be towed away as it's wheels were broken. So we are finally connected and we're on the very end of the plane and some folks being decided to chill in the corridor of the airplane with their toddlers and their bags. Politely we managed to climb through their barricades while avoiding the stink eyes and we made it out to the airport with 20 minutes to spare!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had a 10 minute long sprint through the entire airport looking for Jetstar's booth, but it's nowhere to be found. Finally we found a gate with a small placard saying something related to our journey. There's was a lady standing there and she looked confused when we passed her our phones with flight tickets on them. She asks some questions that we couldn't really make out, we nodded and pointed and weirdly enough we got let through!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;video autoplay="" loop="" muted="" title="We really had to leg it, we even ran on the moving walkways. We really went FAST!" width="480"&gt;&lt;source src="https://granitosaurus.github.io/gifs/sanic.mp4" type="video/mp4"/&gt;&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had our bags checked and had 10 minutes to spare! We went on looking for jetstar's booth again but the info desk just pointed us to the gate from which our plane was about to leave. Well the people at the gate told us that we messed up, "how did you even get here without a boarding pass and without going through immigration?" they asked. We explained our story briefly and luckily for us they took pity on us and we were issued boarding passes right there at the gate, and had 5 minutes left to boot!&lt;br/&gt;
Plan was very calculated to say the least!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last step of our trip was complete! We finally felt relieved, and this final flight between Bangkok and Ho Chi Minh City was the most enjoyable flight of my life - it felt as we're flying first class!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="quest #2: get to the apartment"&gt;Quest #2: Get to the apartment&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We actually landed early, not that it mattered this time. The airport was pleasant and straight-forward. We followed "visa" arrows and finally arrived at the visa issue area, passed our documents and passports to a very bored looking policeman and sat down to wait for our turn.&lt;br/&gt;
Every few minutes you could hear a lady mumble something over the speaker and a bunch of foreigners starting to look confused, trying to decipher whether it was their name mentioned there and whether they should try and shuffle to the window to receive their passports back.&lt;br/&gt;
Finally after 20-or-so minutes our time came and we were called to take our documents and pay up. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All things considered this was one of the most pleasant visa experiences I've had, almost as if it was there just to collect a 25 dollar fee &amp;macr;\_(ツ)_/&amp;macr;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We almost made it. &lt;br/&gt;
Two more steps to go: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exchange some money  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;get to our airbnb place(which was pretty far away.)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we left the gated airport area we were greeted by shouts and offers: "Taxi, Taxi!", "Sim SIM", "Exchange exchange!". We kinda needed all of them but were intimidated by the aggressiveness of the sellers.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;video autoplay="" loop="" muted="" title="1 usd = 26000 dong, we did feel like we were becoming millionaires!" width="480"&gt;&lt;source src="https://granitosaurus.github.io/gifs/spongebob_money.mp4" type="video/mp4"/&gt;&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We looked through the booths by standing far away to avoid the calls and decided on a few. They all offered pretty much the same service. For whatever reason we chose the loud lady at the first booth we saw as she wrote down the biggest number on a paper piece as what she would give us per 1 dollar. We handed her over $500 and she quickly turned us away with a stack of vietnamese dongs as she was about to receive a few more customers. &lt;br/&gt;
We were a bit confused and shocked, so we decided to whip out a calculator and see whether we got scammed. &lt;br/&gt;
After fiddling around we were surprised that we were $60 short! Instead of 12-something million we received only 10. Needless to say we went back to complain and the lady was pretending to be confused: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Oh you wanted this rate on the wall?" (as opposed to my imaginary rate).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She quickly went through her computer, printed us a receipt and handed us the money we were missing. This time we counted every single dong to make sure we got everything.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next we got some sim cards with unlimited data for 150k a pop, it was a pretty good deal, especially compared to european prices. We planned on taking an uber but we got a bit lost on the map and our phone batteries were almost dead. Instead we wrote the address of our place down on a piece of paper before the last electrons evaporated from the lithium batteries and went to a pre-paid taxy booth. It's a booth with some people yelling "Taxi, Taxi" every 30 seconds or so where you pay before you go to prevent being scammed.&lt;br/&gt;
The guys at the booth looked at the address paper confused and said they'll get us there for 200k. We didn't have much choice and 7 euros didn't sound that much for a couple of lost and tired Europeans.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We got the paper went outside and were greeted by a guy who took us to our cab. So we started the last bit of our trip. The streets were just packed and guzzling with motorbikes and here we were sitting in a clearly oversized for this region SUV and dragging along through the tiny streets of Saigon.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://granitosaurus.github.io/gifs/dogo_taxi.gif" title="When everyone is driving a scooter you look a bit of an idiot sitting in an oversized car"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We didn't mind taking our time though. The car was comfy and the views outside were quite mind-blowing! There was a scooter with two people and a dog just standing on the back of it. There was another one with 4 people stacked on it - two parents and two kids. And another one with chickens on it! And the way the whole traffic worked, or didn't. And the way the sidewalks were covered with fruits, produce and even raw meat, occasionally full dead bodies of chicken, ducks and other animals!&lt;br/&gt;
I think we were too tired and jetlagged to have a culture shock, but we definitely felt alien.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://granitosaurus.github.io/images/hcmc_4people_bike.jpg" title="I'm surprised the cheap chinese scooters still manage to survive there"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our driver finally stops, whips out google translate and says that our hotel is somewhere here but it's closed. We correct him that it's not a hotel but he still says it should be somewhere here. We looked around and the place looked familiar and some of the houses even looked like the ones in the pictures our airbnb host sent us - we had the address, surely we can find it.&lt;br/&gt;
As we were about to leave the vehicle our driver used google translate to ask for a $1 tip "for a drink or food". Being tired and just wanting to get away we decided to humor him and give him that dollar.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He wished us goodbye and we set off. We stumbled around looking for our apartment and finally decided to boot up our laptop and charge our phone off it to get maps going. Turns out &lt;strong&gt;we weren't at our destination at all!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
 Google map directions made out an over 500 meter long zig-zag route that we had to take. That doesn't sound like a lot we thought and went forth. Well it was quite a bit, we went through tiny streets filled with scooters and street dogs that followed us around. 20 minutes later we finally arrived there, at least according to the google maps app. However the place was nowhere to be seen. We tried to call our host but our sims were not capable of calls - only online mobile data. Finally we managed to somehow get in touch with our host and we described where we are and he offered to come pick us up in 15 minutes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While waiting and walking around we actually managed to find the place! It was a tall white house with a huge gate on a small side-street nearby. We did it, we got greeted by an old lady that let us in to our apartment and we could lay down on the bed and say for sure that we "made it!".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="lessons learned"&gt;Lessons Learned&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;video autoplay="" loop="" muted="" title="a bunch of obvious conclusions" width="480"&gt;&lt;source src="https://granitosaurus.github.io/gifs/spongebob_book.mp4" type="video/mp4"/&gt;&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general it wasn't as bad as it could have been. I'd say we got lucky at multiple points through out our trip and somewhat unlucky at others. Nevertheless we made it without any losses or injuries and in hindsight it wasn't bad or difficult at all, just &lt;em&gt;inconvenient&lt;/em&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tips for future traveling:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research airport structures. Make sure to get online checkin. Check in as early as possible.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not trust money exchanges.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carry multiple mini-usb cables/power banks for phone charging.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not trust taxi services too much.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finland is weird and expensive.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="travel"></category><category term="vietnam"></category></entry><entry><title>Going to Vietnam!</title><link href="https://granitosaurus.github.io/vietnam.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-11-14T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-11-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Bernardas Ališauskas</name></author><id>tag:granitosaurus.github.io,2017-11-14:/vietnam.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Preparing to spend 3 months in Vietnam, working remotely and experiencing a distance culture - an exciting proposition!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Me and my girlfriend have been planning to spend this year somewhere abroad.
My first choice was Lisbon, Portugal as we visited Porto last year and
I've always wanted to spend a year or two living and experiencing Portugal.
However due to huge house market inflation (what was 500&amp;euro;/month two years ago
turned out to be almost 1000&amp;euro; now) it seemed to be a bit pricey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an alternative we've started to look into South-East Asia, Vietnam and Thailand in particular.
Both of these countries are famous for expats and remote workers. After a bit of
research we've decided to go to Vietnam first as visa is easier to acquire and it's
 both of our first time dealing with visa-required traveling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="vietnam"&gt;Vietnam&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Vietnam size compared to EU" src="https://granitosaurus.github.io/images/vietnam_scale.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choosing a particular place to stay in Vietnam is a challenge on it's own since it's
a long noodle-like country that has surprisingly different environments - from busy,
motor-bike filled streets to white sand islands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ho Chi Minh City" src="https://granitosaurus.github.io/images/hcmc.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ho Chi Minh City (aka Saigon) is the biggest city in there so we decided to stay there for our
first month. It has a large expat community as well as being action packed and busy -
the complete opposite of a small Estonian town we're living in right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can get a nice place in the range of 300-500&amp;euro;/month. There are a few places to look
for great rent deals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Airbnb.com - A lot of the places on airbnb offer monthly or weekly discounts. So despite
airbnb usually having inflated prices compared to the rest of the market it can still contain
a lot of good deals. Also it provides security and allows short term rent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;expat.com - has &lt;a href="http://www.expat.com/en/housing/asia/vietnam/ho-chi-minh-city/"&gt;a lot of listings&lt;/a&gt;.
The only issue is that browsing is really tedious and difficult since there are no search filters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On airbnb we managed to snag a 350&amp;euro; apartment that is close to District 1 which is the city center:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ho Chi Minh City apartment" src="https://granitosaurus.github.io/images/hcmc_apt.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="work"&gt;Work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As there are a lot of remote workers from all around the world in HCMC, there are quite a few
coworking places to choose from.
I found &lt;a href="https://www.coworker.com/vietnam/ho-chi-minh-city"&gt;coworker.com&lt;/a&gt; and it seems that the monthly
prices are in the range of 50-100&amp;euro;. Most of the places offer reasonable scaling for shorter durations,
i.e. 1 week is 1/4 of monthly price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not sure whether I'll go to any of those as I usually just prefer a cafe or a lounge of some sorts,
but nevertheless it could be a good opportunity to meet other expats!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="visa"&gt;Visa&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visa acquisition was as straight-forward as it gets!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just go to &lt;a href="https://www.visatovietnam.org/"&gt;visatovietnam.org&lt;/a&gt;, fill some basic data from your passport,
uncheck unnecessary "fast-forward" fees and pay up 19$ per person (with additional 25$ stamping fee on arrival)
for a 3 month-long single-entry visa. Two days later you'll get a confirmation letter - print out some simple papers,
get a photo of your mug and a scan of your passport and you're ready to go!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="flight"&gt;Flight&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="flight from Tartu to HCMC" src="https://granitosaurus.github.io/images/tartu_hcmc_flight.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flight prices are very reasonable. The month on November this year turned out to be especially cheap.
Our flight is &lt;code&gt;Tartu-Helsinki-Bangkok&lt;/code&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;Bangkok-HCMC&lt;/code&gt;
It's a bit tricky since not many flight searches offer direct flights to HCMC but you can simply organize it
yourself, especially if you do not have any luggage since you don't need to organize luggage transfer.
We bought tickets directly from Finnair and Jetstar. It's a tiny bit more expensive than buying through
various middleman websites but it certainly is safer and easier just to go through the official sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a one-way trip we ended up shelling out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Tartu-Helsinki-Bangkok&lt;/code&gt; - 284&amp;euro;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Bangkok-HCMC&lt;/code&gt; - 66&amp;euro;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is with seat selection near the window.
Grand total of &lt;strong&gt;350&amp;euro;&lt;/strong&gt; is a pretty great deal for traveling half-way to the other side of the world!
And round trip is even cheaper if you're better at planning than I am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="preparation"&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Electrical socket" src="https://granitosaurus.github.io/images/vietnam_socket.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sockets - Vietnam uses different sockets than Europe. There are a few socket-types prevalent but by the looks
of it it's mostly Type A sockets. Vietnam also has different voltages of 110 to 220 V at 50Hz compared to
european 230V @ 50Hz. So in some rare occasions you'll want a power converter as well. However it's probably
easier to get the adapters and/or converters in Vietnam itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aren't really planning on taking anything other than laptops and a camera. There seems to be a decent
amount of snatch and pick pocket crimes but we have a secure backpack
(&lt;a href="https://www.xd-design.com/bobby"&gt;Bobby by XDDesign&lt;/a&gt;) to keep our valuables safe.
Vietnam is known for cheap products, especially when it comes to clothing, so really there's
hardly a need to take anything else, it's more fun to go shopping!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="follow up"&gt;Follow Up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is certainly exciting and I'll be sure to follow up this blog in the near future once we get there on Nov 22nd!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll be sure to include spending reports and such as well.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="travel"></category><category term="vietnam"></category></entry><entry><title>Doom and Stone in Tallinn</title><link href="https://granitosaurus.github.io/doom-tallinn-2017.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Bernardas Ališauskas</name></author><id>tag:granitosaurus.github.io,2017-01-31:/doom-tallinn-2017.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I went to a brilliant doom and stone metal concert in Tallinn, Estonia. Spearheaded by Stoned Jesus itself and back by two brilliant bands from Poland!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm a big fan of doom metal and to my surprise a brilliant rock club "Woodstock" was holding a concert featuring 3 brilliant bands: &lt;a href="https://dopelord.bandcamp.com/"&gt;Dopelord[PL]&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://sunnataofficial.bandcamp.com/"&gt;Sunnata[PL]&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://stonedjesus.bandcamp.com/"&gt;Stoned Jesus[UA]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Procession II" src="https://granitosaurus.github.io/images/doom-tallinn.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've attended Stoned Jesus concert last year at the same place and it was a blast, so even though I wasn't familiar with the other two bands, Stoned Jesus was more than enough to convince me this time.&lt;br/&gt;
I tried to keep the other two bands a surprise and only caved during the long and tedious bus ride to the concert itself. I've listened to the top 3 songs on spotify and was completely stoked! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The club &lt;a href="http://www.rockstars.ee/?s=woodstock"&gt;Woodstock&lt;/a&gt; is pretty small and was totally packed throughout the entirety of the concert, which started at 8:30 and went a bit over midnight, so that's almost 4 hours of hard metal music from three very distinct and brilliant bands! &lt;br/&gt;
We had not only Estonian fans, but also Fins, Russians and even Swedes there. Looking back, I'm very surprised how the club managed to fit in so many people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The band that opened up was &lt;a href="https://dopelord.bandcamp.com/"&gt;Dopelord&lt;/a&gt;, a doom/stone metal band from Poland that was founded back in 2010. They're probably the most doom-like band of the three bands and I couldn't help but feel reminded of my favorite band Electric Wizard which just like Dopelord took inspiration from old movies and witchcraft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe allowfullscreen="" class="center-block" frameborder="0" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/cLyN2EKqbks" title="favorite song of the show" width="560"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second band was &lt;a href="https://sunnataofficial.bandcamp.com/"&gt;Sunnata&lt;/a&gt;, which is also from Poland.&lt;br/&gt;
Sunnata formed in 2008 and overall they sound very much doom, though maybe a bit more on the upbeat side, which is not a bad thing by any means, in fact it was very fitting pacing wise for this particular show. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe allowfullscreen="" class="center-block" frameborder="0" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/DoEIzJaFA1c" title="Favorite sunnatra song" width="560"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a side note I'd like to mention the guitarist's wicked-fabulous hair that had a dedicated fan for full potential. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Sunnata's guitarist" src="https://granitosaurus.github.io/images/sunnata_hair.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third and final band was the star of the show - &lt;a href="https://stonedjesus.bandcamp.com/"&gt;Stoned Jesus&lt;/a&gt;. Definitely the most known band in the show and one of the more known recent bands in the stone rock/metal genre. Some people would disagree with me regarding doom metal(or metal in general) classification, but there are definitely noticeable elements in songs like &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/kKAWz4bIeLg?t=286"&gt;Electric Mistress&lt;/a&gt; and it's especially noticeable during live shows!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a 5-year anniversary of their most well known album Seven Thunders Roar and the band was very sincere and thankful to the fans for the support throughout the years and to quote the vocalist/guitarist Igor Sydorenko: "5 years ago we played in crappy places like this, but with 10 times less people, so thank you for the support!"&lt;br/&gt;
To finish up the show the band played a 20 minute long encore and had a pretty successful stage dive to finish up already exhausted fans!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe allowfullscreen="" class="center-block" frameborder="0" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/iW1jxJ6ISks" title="I'm the mountain!" width="560"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summit it - the show was great and I'd like to publicly thank the bands for coming out this far up to Estonia, Tallinn and delivering such a great show! And would highly recommend, given the opportunity, to check these bands out to anyone both live and online.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's pretty much it, a rather pointless blog but I felt really inspired to share this and publicly thank Dopelord, Sunnata and Stoned Jesus for a great show!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="metal"></category><category term="doom"></category><category term="tallinn"></category></entry><entry><title>Pycon PL + Warsaw report</title><link href="https://granitosaurus.github.io/pycon-pl-after.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-23T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-10-23T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Bernardas Ališauskas</name></author><id>tag:granitosaurus.github.io,2016-10-23:/pycon-pl-after.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Pycon Poland and Warsaw aftermath: a summary of my experience in Pycon Poland and Poland, Warsaw in general.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last year during Euro-Python 2015 someone from PyconPL had an interesting lightning talk about PyconPL, and since that moment I was sold. However I missed it by few days that year. However this year I made it and as a bonus I checked out Warsaw, Poland too!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can check my previous blog post how we got to Warsaw &lt;a href="/pycon-pl.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before going to Pycon me and my girlfriend took two days to look around Warsaw, Poland. Throughout the trip we stayed in 3 airbnb places. The first day we were really surprised how pretty and big Warsaw is. To give a little background, before the trip we did a bunch of research of what to do in Warsaw and we really didn't find much so we didn't have high hopes to begin with, thus the surprise. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So without further ado, here is what I (and in some cases we) think of Warsaw!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="food and prices"&gt;Food and Prices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The city is beautiful and there are so &lt;strong&gt;many restaurants and cafes&lt;/strong&gt;. The first thing we did was go to &lt;a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com/Restaurant_Review-g274856-d8529497-Reviews-Mango_Vegan_Street_Food-Warsaw_Mazovia_Province_Central_Poland.html"&gt;Mango Vegan Street Food&lt;/a&gt; which serves great hummus as well as other vegan dishes at a surprisingly low price, brilliant little place!   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Low price is definitely a recurring theme in Warsaw - everything is surprisingly cheaper than in Estonia or Lithuania.&lt;br/&gt;
I've heard of a saying: "Poland is an eastern-european country with western-european prices" which I heavily disagree with, unless western-europe is cheaper than eastern in this context. Everything in general is at least 20% cheaper than in Estonia, sometimes significantly more and quality doesn't suffer because of it. The selection of foods and products in general is huge too - one of the benefits of being in central Europe I guess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a vegetarian I was surprised by how &lt;strong&gt;many vegetarian places&lt;/strong&gt; and options there are in Warsaw. The vegan trend definitely feels real, which was both a pleasant surprise and a piece of convenience for myself.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Simple Definition of meat&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;the flesh of an animal used as food&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;a type of meat&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;the part of something (such as a nut) that can be eaten&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a side note for vegetarianism itself - I found that a lot of polish people do not consider fish to be meat, which is extremely weird and nonsensical. I've noticed that it's a quite common misunderstanding across Europe and had a very similar thing happen in Spain during my visit for Europython 2015 when the vegetarian sandwich I ordered contained tuna...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also worth noting that a &lt;strong&gt;vegetarian person who eats fish is actually called pescatarian&lt;/strong&gt;. It's a rather peculiar sounding term but it's there for a reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="rurki"&gt;Rurki&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="rurki" src="https://granitosaurus.github.io/images/rurki.jpg"/&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are few traditional Polish dishes, but as someone who's from eastern europe himself, I didn't find them unique or interesting at all. All except one: Rurki.&lt;br/&gt;
Rurki is a waffle roll with sweet cream inside of it. It's pretty simple but boy it's delicious! It's sweet, crunchy and creamy at the same time - a perfect dessert!&lt;br/&gt;
The best rurki we've eat were located in &lt;a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com/Attraction_Review-g274856-d2235946-Reviews-Zlote_Tarasy-Warsaw_Mazovia_Province_Central_Poland.html"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zloty Tarasy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; shopping mall. At the very bottom floor there is a small sweets kiosk that offers the best rurki in the city!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="few cool food joints"&gt;Few Cool Food Joints&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There wasn't that much to do in Warsaw, at least during our trip, so we ate out a lot. Here's a short list of my favourite places, that I highly recommend!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="mango vegan street food"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com/Restaurant_Review-g274856-d8529497-Reviews-Mango_Vegan_Street_Food-Warsaw_Mazovia_Province_Central_Poland.html"&gt;Mango Vegan Street Food&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="mango vegan street food" src="https://media-cdn.tripadvisor.com/media/photo-s/09/c0/d2/6d/mango-vegan-street-food.jpg"/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
As I've mentioned above the place is great. It's quite cheap and the food is great. You can get daily deals (that last whole day) and some weekdays have discounts on some dishes. The food selection isn't great, mostly it's just flavours and variants of few dishes, but it's enough for few visits a week. A great place for a quick snack or a lengthier sit down! &lt;br/&gt;
Personal favourite and highly recommended: Pomegranate Hummus!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="bubbleology"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com/Restaurant_Review-g274856-d7189289-Reviews-Bubbleology-Warsaw_Mazovia_Province_Central_Poland.html"&gt;Bubbleology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="bubbleology" src="https://instagram.fhen1-1.fna.fbcdn.net/t51.2885-15/e35/14711881_1261966857193875_5168882141601202176_n.jpg"/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Bubble tea used to be a pretty huge fad across the whole Europe few years ago. However these days it's no longer even a thing in Estonia or Lithuania. Bubble tea is a tea drink with syrup-like bubbles that you can suck in using bigger than usual straw, it's a mix of a dessert and a drink which seems to be the strategy of the biggest cafe brand Starbucks, so we know it works!  &lt;br/&gt;
There's nothing particularity interesting about this shop other than it's themed as a science lab where bubble tea science happens. They really go all out by even dressing the clerks in lab coats and devising made up bubble tea formulas on the walls.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding the prices - they are somewhat steeper than you'd expect even when Bubble tea in general is considered to be more expensive than it should. 
It wasn't the best bubble tea I had but it was good nevertheless so if you miss bubble tea or even worse - never tried it - check this place out!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="min's onigiri"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.yelp.com/biz/mins-onigiri-warszawa?osq=onigiri"&gt;Min's Onigiri&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="min's onigiri place" src="https://instagram.fhen1-1.fna.fbcdn.net/t51.2885-15/e35/14718290_983459391766489_1937566249529638912_n.jpg"/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Onigiri&lt;/em&gt; is a Japanese rice ball that can be can contain some flavouring in the middle of it and topped of with dry seaweed wrapping. Historically it was invented as food for travelers, so it's a perfect food for tourists!&lt;br/&gt;
I really enjoyed this place, it only serves around 8 kinds of different rice balls and only 3 of them were vegetarian friendly, but all 3 of them were delicious. It also serves miso soup which is more or less bullion alternative Japanese use.&lt;br/&gt;
The onigiri themselves aren't that big, so you most likely want to take several. They are extremely delicious however and the miso + onigiri combo ended up being a perfect autumn food for tourists!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding the prices - it's really reasonable. One rice ball + miso soup ended up being 10 PLN (2.3 euros) and 7 without the soup.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="tel aviv food &amp;amp; wine"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com/Restaurant_Review-g274856-d2619568-Reviews-Tel_Aviv_Food_Wine-Warsaw_Mazovia_Province_Central_Poland.html"&gt;Tel Aviv Food &amp;amp; Wine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="tel aviv restaurant during summer" src="https://s3-media4.fl.yelpcdn.com/bphoto/oGNq8N4egk1fMxpk672_TQ/o.jpg"/&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another vegan place, this time though, it's a quite fancy one. The place itself is pretty close to the center and easy to reach, however it's pretty small so you should avoid going there during peak hours.&lt;br/&gt;
The food is very fancy, but personally I wasn't impressed - it was very pretty but didn't have taste or price value to match it. I think I would reserve this place for more fancy occasions rather than a lunch break or a meet up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="green caffe nero"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.greencaffenero.pl/en/"&gt;Green Caffe Nero&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There really isn't much to say about this place. It's a rather regular caf&amp;eacute;, but it's really &lt;strong&gt;affordable&lt;/strong&gt;, has decent food, tea and coffee, and most importantly it's &lt;strong&gt;quite cozy&lt;/strong&gt; - so it's perfect for tourist stop for a tired, cold and worn-out tourist as myself!&lt;br/&gt;
Sitting down with a cup of hot tea, almost italian sandwich and writing some code or a blog for half an hour is always a pleasant experience, wherever you are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find them pretty much on every corner, sometimes you can even see another one from sitting inside one yourself :D&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="few cool places_1"&gt;Few Cool Places&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we left to Poland we did some research of what to visit but couldn't find much other than war museums that are present in every European city and honestly - they bore me to death. However once we got there we found few places that are definitely worth visiting and here they are!   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;One place I don't mention that might be worth visiting is Copernicus Science Center. The reason why I don't think it's worth mentioning that it's always full of kids and unless you spend a long time in warsaw to find one day that isn't - it's not worth the headache.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="university library"&gt;University Library&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="warsaw library" src="https://media-cdn.tripadvisor.com/media/photo-o/0d/07/2c/13/ogrod-zloty.jpg"/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Library? But we're on vacation! &lt;br/&gt;
Weirdly enough it was probably my favourite place in Warsaw. The main attraction was not the library itself, but what's on top of it! The roof of the library is a beautiful garden with all sorts of growth and shapes that create this unique and cosy atmosphere. &lt;br/&gt;
There were very few people and the weather wasn't that bad. It's near the river so it can get a bit windy, so pack up a scarf!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="technology museum and palace of culture and science"&gt;Technology Museum and Palace of Culture and Science&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Place of Culture and Science image" height="500" src="https://granitosaurus.github.io/images/poland_palace.jpg"/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Palace of Culture and Science was gifted to Poland by Russia after WW2. It's a really beautiful building that since in the very center of Warsaw.&lt;br/&gt;
Aside of being pretty it also hosts a pretty cool Technology museum inside of it.It contains exhibits ranging from old motorcycles to nintendo games and it's really fun!&lt;br/&gt;
Few of the highlights: Space technology exhibit, video games, old vehicles (from bikes to planes)  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="pycon pl_2"&gt;Pycon PL&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="pyconpl 2016" src="https://granitosaurus.github.io/images/pyconpl.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We got there in the morning of Thursday, the first day of the conference. My girlfriend attended &lt;strong&gt;Pyladies&lt;/strong&gt; workshop while I checked us in. I don't think she enjoyed it as much as I thought she would, but it certainly piqued her interest in programming, so it wasn't bad!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hotel is huge - it supports over 1600 guests and takes a bit under 5 minutes just to go from one end of it to the other. The cafeteria was great and served a sizeable selection of dishes for breakfast, lunch and dinner. As a vegetarian I only felt left out for one lunch where everything seemed to contain meat which means I ate a full plate of roasted potatoes - just like home!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first few talks were half interesting and half boring. I feel like with many of the talks tend to be longer than they actually need to and some people tend to dig into details a bit too much - the talks in this pycon were not an exception.&lt;br/&gt;
I think a lot of the presenters miss the point that the talk you are giving should &lt;strong&gt;pique the interest of the listener or tell a story&lt;/strong&gt; rather than try sum up a framework or some technique in 10 slides.&lt;br/&gt;
For this reason, I enjoyed the lightning talks the most though that remains to be true for every conference I've been to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the lunch time I met a Lithuanian which was really surprising. Not only python isn't huge in Lithuania but when I was purchasing the tickets one of the hosts mentioned that I'd be the first and only person from Lithuania to attend PyconPL. I'm glad that it turned out not being the case because Lithuania really needs more Python! (or anything that is not php for that matter :D)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="meeting scrapinghubbers"&gt;Meeting Scrapinghubbers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year scrapinghub wasn't sponsoring the conference thus we didn't have a booth. However there were 3 other scrapinghubbers present in the conference other than myself. We chatted and played board games together and I can firmly say that in the two years that I've spent working in Scrapinghub I haven't met a single dislikeable person there and this conference solidified this experience even more!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shoutout to Pawel and two Michals from scrapinghub who made this conference even more fun than it could have been!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="board and retro games"&gt;Board and Retro Games&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every evening board game event has been held in one of the conference rooms and that's probably where the majority of the conference was spent. There was a board game rental company that provided the conference with some board games as well as some people bringing their own. We brought Exploding Kittens, Loot Letter and Coup. Exploding Kittens by far received the most attention, though the other two games weren't far behind too.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="polish Mysterium" src="https://granitosaurus.github.io/images/polish_mysterium.jpg"/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
We didn't get a chance to play any board games that we haven't touched previously with the exception of &lt;strong&gt;Mysterium&lt;/strong&gt;! Or at least Polish version of it, which is the original version of the game and by some considered to be superior. It's a brilliant coop game where one player is a ghost who was hanged for a murder he did not commit and has gives hints to the other players of who was the real murderer! Some people describe it as reverse Dix It which in a way it is, but in my opinion, much more fun and engaging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Donkey Konga for gamecube" src="http://media.ign.com/games/image/object/572/572741/Donkey-Konga-1_Game-and-Bongos_Cube_US_ESRB.jpg"/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Another cool piece of entertainment was retro computer games, a full room of them! They had various consoles and computers ranging from atari to windows 95 Worms Armageddon machines. There were open and running through the whole day and you could play something in-between the talks or after having lunch. My personal favorite was Donkey Konga - a party, rhythm game for GameCube. It's like guitar hero but instead of a guitars, players use a set of bongo drums which create a hilarious and often silly atmosphere!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="summary_2"&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially we didn't find much to do when we did research about Warsaw, however once we got there we got pleasantly surprised by the city and what it offered!  The city is big and beautiful. The center is structured in nice blocks that are easy to traverse and navigate. Every block being full of various small shops, caf&amp;eacute;s or restaurants. And even though there were indeed only few experience places we enjoyed them greatly!&lt;br/&gt;
Pycon was a blast too! The educational opportunities weren't that great (the talks, workshops etc.) but the board games and leisure activities were more than enough to compensate!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will definitely consider going next year! &lt;br/&gt;
Only regret was not taking more luggage.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="pycon"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="poland"></category><category term="travel"></category><category term="warsaw"></category></entry><entry><title>Going to Pycon Poland!</title><link href="https://granitosaurus.github.io/pycon-pl.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-10T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-10-10T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Bernardas Ališauskas</name></author><id>tag:granitosaurus.github.io,2016-10-10:/pycon-pl.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Going to Pycon PL and checking out Warsaw!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last year in Euro-Python 2015 someone from PyconPL had a lightning talk about PyconPL and since that moment I was sold. However I missed it by few days. This year however, I'm going and I'm taking a short vacation to explore Warsaw too!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a bunch of info about the conference on the &lt;a href="https://pl.pycon.org/2016/about_en.html"&gt;official page&lt;/a&gt; and I don't want to be redundant, but the venue looks awesome and in overall the event looks pretty huge. Primarily I just wanted to share how much money do you need to attend something like this, how do you get there and lastly whether it is worth it.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="the route"&gt;The route&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Trip route from Tartu to Warsaw" src="https://granitosaurus.github.io/images/pycon-pl-travel.png"/&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we're taking a bus from Tartu -&amp;gt; Riga which is really the most tedious part of this trip. As you can see in the image the trip almost takes &lt;strong&gt;4 hours&lt;/strong&gt; and the bus leaves early and often is packed full. We'll spend two hours in Riga's airport waiting for our flight, which I really don't mind since Riga's airport is really nice. And to finish it off we'll take a &lt;strong&gt;1.25&lt;/strong&gt; hour long flight to Warsaw itself. I love flying, more accurately I like take offs and landings so having such short flights, where majority of the time will be the take off and the landing, sounds great!&lt;br/&gt;
In conclusion, we leave at 7:00 and we should be in Warsaw at 14:35 (warsaw's time). So this ends up being &lt;strong&gt;8.5 hours for 900km&lt;/strong&gt; which really doesn't have a good hour/km ratio per se but considering the down-times and the location it really isn't bad at all! &lt;br/&gt;
Lastly the conference organizes a bus that will take us from Warsaw to Ossa village, which is few kilometers away from Warsaw and there the conference itself will be held. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="the cost"&gt;The Cost&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3 id="conference"&gt;Conference&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I was a bit late to register and missed the early bird prices, I had to drop 211&amp;euro; per person (422&amp;euro; for two people) for 4 days of the conference, including food and accommodation. This might seem like a lot but compared to other conferences is really little. &lt;br/&gt;
I actually chatted with one of the hosts a bit and he mentioned that pretty much the whole fee goes to the hotel that is hosting the conference, after visiting the website I can understand that since it advertises the rooms at 90&amp;euro; a night the conference fee seems to be very reasonable indeed!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="travel"&gt;Travel&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plane tickets from Riga to Warsaw and back ended up being 62&amp;euro; per person(125&amp;euro; for two) which is slightly above from the best I could find. At one point I got 42&amp;euro; deals pop up but the payment didn't go through and the next day it popped to 62&amp;euro;. I know airline websites are really fishy when it comes to pricing, storing profiles and cookies to jack up the price whenever they see fit but I'm certain this was just an unfortunate coincidence.&lt;br/&gt;
The bus to Riga from Tartu ended up being 30&amp;euro; per person (60&amp;euro; in total) both ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So &lt;strong&gt;total ended up being 303&amp;euro; per person&lt;/strong&gt; which is pretty cheap for a conference 906km away!&lt;br/&gt;
This doesn't include any traveling expenses which I'll be sure to calculated and include in aftermath blogpost!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last python conference I went to was EuroPython 2015 and it was super fun, mostly because I got to meet a bunch of coworkers from Scrapinghub, I hope PyconPL can live up to the hype and I'll be sure to post about it either way.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="pycon"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="poland"></category><category term="travel"></category></entry></feed>